<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[RayHightower.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-09-01T21:31:47-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://RayHightower.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Raymond T. Hightower - Chicago Ruby on Rails & iOS Developer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Four Steps. Five Minutes.]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2012/08/31/four-steps-five-minutes/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-31T15:04:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2012/08/31/four-steps-five-minutes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Nine out of ten startups fail in the first year. Why? More important, what can we do to improve the odds? Entrepreneur Steve Blank might have an answer, expressed in his book <em>The Four Steps to the Epiphany</em>. Key points from the book are summarized here.</p>

<h4>Ignite Chicago</h4>

<p>This presentation was created for <a href="http://ignitechi.org">Ignite Chicago</a>. Ignite talks are special because speakers are required to present their thoughts in five minutes with slides that auto-advance every fifteen seconds. Thank you Stella Fayman and Tim Jahn for organizing the event.</p>

<center><iframe width="560" height="349" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/uIYUTKP1pl8?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></center>




<!-- more -->


<h4>About the Author of <em>The Four Steps to the Epiphany</em></h4>

<p><a href="http://steveblank.com">Steve Blank</a> worked in, owned, or managed eight different silicon valley startups in the course of twenty years. His eighth startup was very successful; he was able to exit with enough money to retire. At that point, Blank began to reflect on the successes and failures of the various startups he had been involved with. Reflection led to lectures at Stanford, Berkeley, and Columbia. Notes from his lectures evolved into the book: <em>The Four Steps to the Epiphany</em>.</p>

<p>Blank noticed that startups went through predictable patterns of success or failure. Yes, there are multiple paths to failure, but there are fewer paths to success. Blank believes he has found a success path that applies to most startups.</p>

<h4>Counter Example: Webvan</h4>

<p>Sometimes it helps to explain an idea through counter example. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Webvan">Webvan</a> was built to deliver groceries to people who ordered on the web. The problem? Webvan built software and warehouses before they had a reliable supply of customers. They were so confident of their future success that they spent close to one billion dollars building infrastructure. They ran out of money before they had customers.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s not fair to pick on Webvan when so many other companies make the same mistake. Remember the Apple Newton? Apple is a great company, but they put tons of money into an early PDA (the Newton) before customers even knew what a PDA was. Same with Motorola. Motorola’s Iridium was supposed to be a network of communications satellites covering the planet. Satellites designed to give internet and phone access to every human on planet earth. The problem: Nobody could afford Iridium. In these examples, Motorola, Apple, and Webvan, all burned through money before they had a steady supply of customers. There is a better way.</p>

<h4>The Four Steps</h4>

<p>Steve Blank lists <em>The Four Steps to the Epiphany</em> as:</p>

<blockquote>
  1. Customer Discovery<br/>
  2. Customer Validation<br/>
  3. Customer Creation<br/>
  4. Company Building<br/>
</blockquote>


<p>There are a few things to point out about the steps. First the process is iterative, not linear. If at any point we get stuck, we go back and repeat a step (or two) based on what we&#8217;ve learned. A smaller repetition might be termed an iteration. But if the entrepreneur needs to revisit the entire business plan, or change basic assumptions in the business model, the repetition/backtracking would be termed a <em>pivot</em>.</p>

<h4>Customer Discovery and the Minimum Viable Product</h4>

<p>Every entrepreneur has an idea about what customers want. We all know something of the pain felt by our customers, or so we think. Blank&#8217;s suggestion: Take what you know about your prospective customers&#8217; pain and build a minimum viable product (MVP) with just enough features to address the pain. Then get outside the building. Get away from wherever it is that you work and talk to real customers with your MVP in hand. Let them try it. They&#8217;ll give you valuable feedback about what you should do next. If their pain is great enough, and if your MVP is good enough, they&#8217;ll buy it.</p>

<h4>Which Customers?<a href="http://RayHightower.com/images/lifecycle.png" onclick="window.open('/images/lifecycle.png','popup','width=770,height=548,scrollbars=no,resizable=yes,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0'); return false"><img src="http://RayHightower.com/images/lifecycle_thumb.png" border="0" alt="Technology Adoption Lifecycle, Crossing the Chasm, Geoffrey Moore" name="image" class="right" width="195" height="137" title="Technology Adoption Lifecycle, Crossing the Chasm, Geoffrey Moore" /></a></h4>

<p>It&#8217;s important to note the type of customer we want at this stage. We want early adopters. We want customers who are feeling pain in the entrepreneur&#8217;s area of expertise. Perhaps customers who have tried to solve the problem themselves with no success. Early adopters will give us the most useful &amp; actionable feedback at this stage.</p>

<h4>Customer Validation</h4>

<p>The customer validation step is complete when early adopters buy the product we&#8217;re offering. When customers buy, we know we have a valid product. If they don&#8217;t buy, it might be time to pivot. In this context, <em>pivot</em> means to change the basic assumptions of the business we&#8217;re building. We might change pricing, features, or we might change our entire approach to customers. Many startups go through several pivots before achieving success.</p>

<h4>Customer Creation</h4>

<p>After we&#8217;ve discovered customers, and after we&#8217;ve gone through customer validation, it&#8217;s time to create more customers. Our initial customers were the early adopters and innovators. In the customer creation step, we move beyond our initial customers into the majority. At this point we begin to spend money on marketing.</p>

<h4>Company Building</h4>

<p>After we&#8217;ve gone through the first three customer-oriented steps, we build the company. Now it&#8217;s time to spend money on infrastructure, warehouses, expensive customized software&#8230; anything we need to scale the company as large as we can. Notice that we don&#8217;t try to scale until after we figure out how to develop a steady supply of customers.</p>

<h4>That&#8217;s Not All&#8230;</h4>

<p>We live in a time of continuous &amp; rapid change. Once a business has become successful with <em>The Four Steps</em>, it&#8217;s important to remain watchful for new opportunities. Good companies become great when they execute consistently over time.</p>

<p><em>Note: A version of this post originally appeared on the <a href="http://wisdomgroup.com">WisdomGroup Blog</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Down Is Mandatory]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2012/08/26/getting-down-is-mandatory/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-26T16:55:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2012/08/26/getting-down-is-mandatory</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://RayHightower.com/images/climber.jpg" title="No Shortcuts to the Top by Ed Viesturs" alt="Book cover: No Shortcuts to the Top by Ed Viesturs">
<a href="http://www.charlierose.com/">Charlie Rose</a> is an amazing journalist. His interviews are eclectic and rich. During his interview with mountain climber Ed Viesturs, I was struck by the parallels between mountain climbing and business achievement.</p>

<h4>Managing Risk, Ignoring Critics</h4>

<p>“People say that I’m a very conservative and cautious climber,” says Viesturs. “It’s true, and I’m happy about that because it’s a risky arena and it’s about managing the risk and being smart and being patient. The people who criticize me have no idea what they’re talking about. They’ve never climbed an 8,000-foot peak. So they’re either jealous or bored. My goal is to be alive. And I don’t care about critics.”</p>

<p><em>Business Parallel:</em> Our most successful entrepreneurs press onward in the face of criticism.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h4>Life and Death, Navigating Change</h4>

<p>Climbers operate in an environment where sound preparation and conditioning makes the difference between life and death. True, some unprepared climbers find that they must simply turn around and go back home. On one peak in the Himalayas, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Annapurna">Annaperna</a>, one out of every two climbers dies while attempting the climb.</p>

<p>Changes in snow conditions and weather are the biggest threats to success. A climber must be very aware of the deadly combination of heavy snow and strong wind: Avalanche conditions. With the right combination of heavy snow and strong wind, a climber moving about in the wrong spot (or any spot) can trigger an avalanche.</p>

<p><em>Business Parallel:</em> Changes in business climate can make the difference between massive success and crushing defeat. It all depends on how well you respond to (or even better, anticipate) change.</p>

<h4>Getting Down is Mandatory</h4>

<p>Along the pathway to success, Viesturs has tasted bitter setbacks. During a climb of Mount Everest, he and his team were 300 feet from the summit. And then he noticed a change in the weather. Conditions were ripe for a potential avalanche. He realized that if the team pressed on to the top of the mountain, they wouldn’t have time to make it down. His trademark phrase came from this experience: “Getting to the summit is optional, getting down is mandatory. It has to be a round trip.” Viesturs and team turned around and they went back home. And they lived to scale Everest another day.</p>

<p><em>Business Parallel:</em> One doesn’t have to bet the company on every new business initiative. Testing takes time, but the wisdom absorbed from test results can increase the odds of success.</p>

<h4>Having the Right Goals</h4>

<p>It’s good to be aggressive about achieving goals. But sometimes we need to shift our goals backwards in favor of human compassion. Viesturs and Rose recounted a story about a climber who lay injured along the pathway toward a mountain peak. Over forty (40) climbers passed the injured climber without offering assistance. Each felt that the climber was so badly injured that he was going to die anyway. Besides, they had goals to achieve.</p>

<p><em>Business Parallel:</em> If you’re a successful entrepreneur and you’re rolling in dough, when was the last time you spent time teaching our youth how to follow in your footsteps?</p>

<h4>Why Climbing Fascinates Us</h4>

<p>Toward the end of the interview, Rose asks, &#8220;What is it about mountain climbing that captures our imagination?&#8221;</p>

<p>Viesturs’ response:</p>

<blockquote><p>It’s about plugging away at something that looks almost impossible. It’s about looking at something from the beginning to an end that seems almost unachievable. And then achieving that end.<br/></p>

<p>When I speak to corporate groups [about achieving a goal], my message is that if you’re passionate about it,<br/>
if you have a good team,<br/>
if you enjoy the process,<br/>
if you break it into steps,<br/>
you can achieve amazing things if you have the patience to do so.<br/></p></blockquote>

<p>Amazing things indeed.</p>

<p><em>Note: A version of this post originally appeared on the <a href="http://wisdomgroup.com">WisdomGroup Blog</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
