<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[RayHightower.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-09-01T08:23:32-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://RayHightower.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Raymond T. Hightower - Chicago Ruby on Rails & iOS Developer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[10,000 Hours of Practice]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2012/09/04/10000-hours-of-practice/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-04T00:46:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2012/09/04/10000-hours-of-practice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the book <em>Outliers</em>, author Malcolm Gladwell says that it takes roughly ten thousand hours of practice to achieve mastery in a field. How does Gladwell arrive at this conclusion? And, if the conclusion is true, how can we leverage this idea to achieve greatness in our professions?</p>

<p>Gladwell studied the lives of extremely successful people to find out how they achieved success. This article will review a few examples from Gladwell’s research, and conclude with some thoughts for moving forward.</p>

<h4>Violins in Berlin</h4>

<p>In the early 1990s a team of psychologists in Berlin, Germany studied violin students. Specifically, they studied their practice habits in childhood, adolescence, and adulthood. All of the subjects were asked this question: “Over the course of your entire career, ever since you first picked up the violin, how many hours have you practiced?”</p>

<p>All of the violinists had begun playing at roughly five years of age with similar practice times. However, at age eight, practice times began to diverge. By age twenty, the elite performers averaged more than 10,000 hours of practice each, while the less able performers had only 4,000 hours of practice.</p>

<p>The elite had more than double the practice hours of the less capable performers.</p>

<h4>Natural Talent: Not Important</h4>

<p>One fascinating point of the study: No “naturally gifted” performers emerged. If natural talent had played a role, we would expect some of the “naturals” to float to the top of the elite level with fewer practice hours than everyone else. But the data showed otherwise. The psychologists found a direct statistical relationship between hours of practice and achievement. No shortcuts. No naturals.</p>

<h4>Sneaking Out to Write Code</h4>

<p>You already know how Microsoft was founded. Bill Gates and Paul Allen dropped out of college to form the company in 1975. It’s that simple: Drop out of college, start a company, and become a billionaire, right? Wrong.</p>

<p>Further study reveals that Gates and Allen had thousands of hours of programming practice prior to founding Microsoft. First, the two co-founders met at Lakeside, an elite private school in the Seattle area. The school raised three thousand dollars to purchase a computer terminal for the school’s computer club in 1968.</p>

<p>A computer terminal at a <em>university</em> was rare in 1968. Gates had access to a terminal in <em>eighth grade</em>. Gates and Allen quickly became addicted to programming.</p>

<p>The Gates family lived near the University of Washington. As a teenager, Gates fed his programming addiction by sneaking out of his parents’ home after bedtime to use the University’s computer. Gates &amp; Allen acquired their10,000 hours through this and other clever teenage schemes. When the time came to launch Microsoft in 1975, the two were ready.</p>

<h4>Practice Makes Improvement</h4>

<p>In 1960, while they were still an unknown high school rock band, the Beatles went to Hamburg, Germany to play in the local clubs.</p>

<p>The group was underpaid. The acoustics were terrible. The audiences were unappreciative. So what did the Beatles get out of the Hamburg experience? Hours of playing time. Non-stop hours of playing time that forced them to get better.</p>

<p>As the Beatles grew in skill, audiences demanded more performances - more playing time. By 1962 they were playing eight hours per night, seven nights per week. By 1964, the year they burst on the international scene, the Beatles had played over 1,200 concerts together. By way of comparison, most bands today don’t play 1,200 times in their <em>entire career</em>.</p>

<h4>Falling in Love With Practice</h4>

<p>The elite don’t just work harder than everybody else. At some point the elites fall in love with practice to the point where they want to do little else.</p>

<p>The elite software developer is the programmer who spends all day pounding code at work, and after leaving work she writes open source software on her own time.</p>

<p>The elite football player is the guy who spends all day on the practice field with his teammates, and after practice he goes home to watch game films.</p>

<p>The elite physician listens to medical podcasts in the car during a long commute.</p>

<p>The elites are in love with what they do, and at some point it no longer feels like work.</p>

<h4>What’s Next?</h4>

<p>Now that we’ve reviewed the trends uncovered by Gladwell’s research, what can we do about it? All of us want to be great at something. Now that we know how other achievers have gotten there, what can we do to join their ranks?</p>

<p>One approach: We could choose a field and practice for 10,000 hours. If we are currently working in our target profession, forty hours per week over five years would give us ten thousand hours.</p>

<p>Or&#8230; We can look at the question in reverse. Where have we already logged 10,000 hours of practice? What is it that we do really well? What tasks do we perform so well that people ask: How did you do that? Sometimes when we fall in love with practice we don’t even recognize it!</p>

<p>If you’re running a company, what does your company do better than anybody else? What is it that the individual members of your company do better than anybody? How do you create an environment that gives everyone on your team the opportunity to practice?</p>

<h4>Conclusion</h4>

<p>Business is tough, especially now. Yet even in the midst of a challenging economy, there are individuals and companies that prosper beyond all expectations. Practice plays a major role in success.</p>

<h4>Suggested Reading</h4>

<p><em>Outliers</em>, by Malcolm Gladwell. Through interviews and statistical analysis, Gladwell determines why some people and organizations achieve success far beyond their peers.</p>

<p><em>Note: A version of this post was originally published at <a href="http://wisdomgroup.com">WisdomGroup.com</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Business View of Ruby on Rails]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2012/09/01/a-business-view-of-ruby-on-rails/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-01T01:03:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2012/09/01/a-business-view-of-ruby-on-rails</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h4>You Will Hear About This</h4>

<p>If your business uses Web-based software (also known as webware), you will hear about Ruby on Rails. This newsletter will answer three questions:</p>

<ul>
<li>What is Ruby on Rails?</li>
<li>Why do you care?</li>
<li>How can you benefit?</li>
</ul>


<h4>What is Ruby on Rails?</h4>

<p>Ruby on Rails (&#8220;Rails&#8221; or &#8220;RoR&#8221; for short) helps developers write better webware in less time. Clients appreciate results, and Rails enables developers to deliver in a big way.</p>

<p>RoR consists of two components: an object oriented programming language called Ruby, and a Web development framework called Rails.</p>

<h4>Ruby: The Language</h4>

<p>Ruby is the object oriented language dominant in Rails applications. Many developers believe that software written in object oriented languages is easier to maintain.</p>

<p>Your company can benefit from the object oriented approach because easier maintenance means a longer, revenue-generating lifespan for your webware.</p>

<p>Wikipedia.com has a great discussion of object oriented languages for those who want more details.</p>

<h4>Rails: The Framework</h4>

<p>One of the best ways to define Rails is to describe the problem that it solves.</p>

<p>The problem: Creating a Web-based application can be very time-consuming because of all the details that must be tracked and managed.</p>

<p>As users, we take well-built webware for granted. However, every element of every page must be clearly defined and thoroughly tested before users visit the site. Every text box, every drop-down arrow, every data field (credit card number, expiration date, etc.) must be programmed and thoroughly tested before any users visit the site.</p>

<h4>Rails Automates Repeated Tasks</h4>

<p>Rails automates time-consuming, repetitive tasks (things that were once done manually) so that developers can focus on solving problems for your business.</p>

<p>Here&#8217;s an example from another profession. Can you imagine an accountant&#8217;s life without a spreadsheet like Microsoft Excel or Lotus 1-2-3? Maybe you don&#8217;t have to imagine! You might recall the days of paper spreadsheets, pencils, and 10-key hand-cranked calculators.</p>

<p>Rails is to software developers as electronic spreadsheets are to accountants. Both tools make their respective professionals more productive by eliminating repetitive tasks (grunt work).</p>

<h4>Limitations of Rails</h4>

<p>Rails and spreadsheets both eliminate grunt work. At the same time, they both have limitations.</p>

<p>Neither is a replacement for rational thought. For example, knowing how to use a spreadsheet won&#8217;t make you an accountant because you still need to understand tax law and discounted cash flow analysis.</p>

<p>Likewise, a developer who knows Rails must also understand object oriented programming and relational database theory in order to create a workable piece of software.</p>

<p>A spreadsheet won&#8217;t make you an accountant, Rails won&#8217;t make you a Web developer, and a big hat in Texas won&#8217;t make you a cowboy!</p>

<h4>Other Options</h4>

<p>By the way, there are other frameworks. There are other languages. Rails is the latest in a long line of tools designed to make programmers more productive. History shows that the tools will continue to improve over time.</p>

<h4>Why Do You Care?</h4>

<p>You care because in the end, results matter. Further, if there&#8217;s a way for your developers to achieve better results with better tools, then tools matter too. Rails is not a panacea for all Web development. You&#8217;ve heard the saying &#8220;If the only tool you have is a hammer, every problem looks like a nail.&#8221; Be sure that the developer you choose understands the tool in use and why it was chosen. This may save you headaches in the end.</p>

<h4>Evaluating Developer Skills</h4>

<p>One good way to measure your developer&#8217;s skills: Take a look at projects the developer has completed in the past. Were the clients satisfied? How did the developer handle problems? A good developer, like a good craftsman, will be willing to talk to you about tools and methodologies. The more comfortable you are with the developer and the tools, the greater the chances of project success.</p>

<p>As of this writing, Wisdom has three Rails applications under development. You can check our web site for real-time information about our Rails applications.</p>

<h4>How Can You Benefit?</h4>

<p>Maybe you can&#8217;t. Some business processes are best handled by off-the shelf software. Bookkeeping, for example, is one area where there&#8217;s a penalty for creativity so it&#8217;s better to do what the government and your investors want you to do.</p>

<p>But keep this in mind. If you&#8217;re running your most critical business processes with off-the-shelf software, so can your competitors. A company that does not stand out from its competitors runs the risk of being commoditized. And all commodities are subject to low profit margins.</p>

<h4>Good Ideas, Amplified</h4>

<p>Good ideas are amplified when implemented in good software. If you have a bold &amp; innovative business idea, if your idea can be monetized, and if your idea is so unique that it does not exist in off-the-shelf form, then custom Webware in the Rails framework might fit you.</p>

<h4>One More Thing&#8230;</h4>

<p>Rails is a tool for creating webware, and webware runs virtually anywhere! Rails applications are designed to run inside a simple web browser like Microsoft Internet Explorer or Apple Safari. You can even find browsers on personal digital assistants (PDAs).</p>

<p>Imagine the benefit of using the same business software on your PC, Macintosh, and PDA! No new interface to learn, and no special installation steps for each platform.</p>

<p>Advantages of Webware are discussed further in the 2Q2007 issue of The Wisdom Report entitled &#8220;Webware ROI&#8221;:/report/webware_roi/.</p>

<h4>Suggested Reading</h4>

<p><em>Programming Ruby</em> by Dave Thomas. Anyone who wants to write Rails code must know Ruby. This title is available in paper form and as a downloadable PDF from the publisher.</p>

<p><em>Agile Web Development With Rails</em> by Dave Thomas, Mike Clark, and several other authors. This title builds upon the Ruby book above. Also available in paper and PDF formats.</p>

<p><em>Note: A version of this post was originally published at <a href="http://wisdomgroup.com">WisdomGroup.com</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Four Steps. Five Minutes.]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2012/08/31/four-steps-five-minutes/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-31T15:04:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2012/08/31/four-steps-five-minutes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Nine out of ten startups fail in the first year. Why? More important, what can we do to improve the odds? Entrepreneur Steve Blank might have an answer, expressed in his book <em>The Four Steps to the Epiphany</em>. Key points from the book are summarized here.</p>

<h4>Ignite Chicago</h4>

<p>This presentation was created for <a href="http://ignitechi.org">Ignite Chicago</a>. Ignite talks are special because speakers are required to present their thoughts in five minutes with slides that auto-advance every fifteen seconds. Thank you Stella Fayman and Tim Jahn for organizing the event.</p>

<center><iframe width="560" height="349" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/uIYUTKP1pl8?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></center>


<h4>About the Author of <em>The Four Steps to the Epiphany</em></h4>

<p><a href="http://steveblank.com">Steve Blank</a> worked in, owned, or managed eight different silicon valley startups in the course of twenty years. His eighth startup was very successful; he was able to exit with enough money to retire. At that point, Blank began to reflect on the successes and failures of the various startups he had been involved with. Reflection led to lectures at Stanford, Berkeley, and Columbia. Notes from his lectures evolved into the book: <em>The Four Steps to the Epiphany</em>.</p>

<p>Blank noticed that startups went through predictable patterns of success or failure. Yes, there are multiple paths to failure, but there are fewer paths to success. Blank believes he has found a success path that applies to most startups.</p>

<h4>Counter Example: Webvan</h4>

<p>Sometimes it helps to explain an idea through counter example. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Webvan">Webvan</a> was built to deliver groceries to people who ordered on the web. The problem? Webvan built software and warehouses before they had a reliable supply of customers. They were so confident of their future success that they spent close to one billion dollars building infrastructure. They ran out of money before they had customers.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s not fair to pick on Webvan when so many other companies make the same mistake. Remember the Apple Newton? Apple is a great company, but they put tons of money into an early PDA (the Newton) before customers even knew what a PDA was. Same with Motorola. Motorola’s Iridium was supposed to be a network of communications satellites covering the planet. Satellites designed to give internet and phone access to every human on planet earth. The problem: Nobody could afford Iridium. In these examples, Motorola, Apple, and Webvan, all burned through money before they had a steady supply of customers. There is a better way.</p>

<h4>The Four Steps</h4>

<p>Steve Blank lists <em>The Four Steps to the Epiphany</em> as:</p>

<blockquote>
  1. Customer Discovery<br/>
  2. Customer Validation<br/>
  3. Customer Creation<br/>
  4. Company Building<br/>
</blockquote>


<p>There are a few things to point out about the steps. First the process is iterative, not linear. If at any point we get stuck, we go back and repeat a step (or two) based on what we&#8217;ve learned. A smaller repetition might be termed an iteration. But if the entrepreneur needs to revisit the entire business plan, or change basic assumptions in the business model, the repetition/backtracking would be termed a <em>pivot</em>.</p>

<h4>Customer Discovery and the Minimum Viable Product</h4>

<p>Every entrepreneur has an idea about what customers want. We all know something of the pain felt by our customers, or so we think. Blank&#8217;s suggestion: Take what you know about your prospective customers&#8217; pain and build a minimum viable product (MVP) with just enough features to address the pain. Then get outside the building. Get away from wherever it is that you work and talk to real customers with your MVP in hand. Let them try it. They&#8217;ll give you valuable feedback about what you should do next. If their pain is great enough, and if your MVP is good enough, they&#8217;ll buy it.</p>

<h4>Which Customers?<a href="http://RayHightower.com/images/lifecycle.png" onclick="window.open('/images/lifecycle.png','popup','width=770,height=548,scrollbars=no,resizable=yes,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0'); return false"><img src="http://RayHightower.com/images/lifecycle_thumb.png" border="0" alt="Technology Adoption Lifecycle, Crossing the Chasm, Geoffrey Moore" name="image" class="right" width="195" height="137" title="Technology Adoption Lifecycle, Crossing the Chasm, Geoffrey Moore" /></a></h4>

<p>It&#8217;s important to note the type of customer we want at this stage. We want early adopters. We want customers who are feeling pain in the entrepreneur&#8217;s area of expertise. Perhaps customers who have tried to solve the problem themselves with no success. Early adopters will give us the most useful &amp; actionable feedback at this stage.</p>

<h4>Customer Validation</h4>

<p>The customer validation step is complete when early adopters buy the product we&#8217;re offering. When customers buy, we know we have a valid product. If they don&#8217;t buy, it might be time to pivot. In this context, <em>pivot</em> means to change the basic assumptions of the business we&#8217;re building. We might change pricing, features, or we might change our entire approach to customers. Many startups go through several pivots before achieving success.</p>

<h4>Customer Creation</h4>

<p>After we&#8217;ve discovered customers, and after we&#8217;ve gone through customer validation, it&#8217;s time to create more customers. Our initial customers were the early adopters and innovators. In the customer creation step, we move beyond our initial customers into the majority. At this point we begin to spend money on marketing.</p>

<h4>Company Building</h4>

<p>After we&#8217;ve gone through the first three customer-oriented steps, we build the company. Now it&#8217;s time to spend money on infrastructure, warehouses, expensive customized software&#8230; anything we need to scale the company as large as we can. Notice that we don&#8217;t try to scale until after we figure out how to develop a steady supply of customers.</p>

<h4>That&#8217;s Not All&#8230;</h4>

<p>We live in a time of continuous &amp; rapid change. Once a business has become successful with <em>The Four Steps</em>, it&#8217;s important to remain watchful for new opportunities. Good companies become great when they execute consistently over time.</p>

<p><em>Note: A version of this post originally appeared on the <a href="http://wisdomgroup.com">WisdomGroup Blog</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Down Is Mandatory]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2012/08/26/getting-down-is-mandatory/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-26T16:55:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2012/08/26/getting-down-is-mandatory</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://RayHightower.com/images/climber.jpg" title="No Shortcuts to the Top by Ed Viesturs" alt="Book cover: No Shortcuts to the Top by Ed Viesturs">
<a href="http://www.charlierose.com/">Charlie Rose</a> is an amazing journalist. His interviews are eclectic and rich. During his interview with mountain climber Ed Viesturs, I was struck by the parallels between mountain climbing and business achievement.</p>

<h4>Managing Risk, Ignoring Critics</h4>

<p>“People say that I’m a very conservative and cautious climber,” says Viesturs. “It’s true, and I’m happy about that because it’s a risky arena and it’s about managing the risk and being smart and being patient. The people who criticize me have no idea what they’re talking about. They’ve never climbed an 8,000-foot peak. So they’re either jealous or bored. My goal is to be alive. And I don’t care about critics.”</p>

<p><em>Business Parallel:</em> Our most successful entrepreneurs press onward in the face of criticism.</p>

<h4>Life and Death, Navigating Change</h4>

<p>Climbers operate in an environment where sound preparation and conditioning makes the difference between life and death. True, some unprepared climbers find that they must simply turn around and go back home. On one peak in the Himalayas, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Annapurna">Annaperna</a>, one out of every two climbers dies while attempting the climb.</p>

<p>Changes in snow conditions and weather are the biggest threats to success. A climber must be very aware of the deadly combination of heavy snow and strong wind: Avalanche conditions. With the right combination of heavy snow and strong wind, a climber moving about in the wrong spot (or any spot) can trigger an avalanche.</p>

<p><em>Business Parallel:</em> Changes in business climate can make the difference between massive success and crushing defeat. It all depends on how well you respond to (or even better, anticipate) change.</p>

<h4>Getting Down is Mandatory</h4>

<p>Along the pathway to success, Viesturs has tasted bitter setbacks. During a climb of Mount Everest, he and his team were 300 feet from the summit. And then he noticed a change in the weather. Conditions were ripe for a potential avalanche. He realized that if the team pressed on to the top of the mountain, they wouldn’t have time to make it down. His trademark phrase came from this experience: “Getting to the summit is optional, getting down is mandatory. It has to be a round trip.” Viesturs and team turned around and they went back home. And they lived to scale Everest another day.</p>

<p><em>Business Parallel:</em> One doesn’t have to bet the company on every new business initiative. Testing takes time, but the wisdom absorbed from test results can increase the odds of success.</p>

<h4>Having the Right Goals</h4>

<p>It’s good to be aggressive about achieving goals. But sometimes we need to shift our goals backwards in favor of human compassion. Viesturs and Rose recounted a story about a climber who lay injured along the pathway toward a mountain peak. Over forty (40) climbers passed the injured climber without offering assistance. Each felt that the climber was so badly injured that he was going to die anyway. Besides, they had goals to achieve.</p>

<p><em>Business Parallel:</em> If you’re a successful entrepreneur and you’re rolling in dough, when was the last time you spent time teaching our youth how to follow in your footsteps?</p>

<h4>Why Climbing Fascinates Us</h4>

<p>Toward the end of the interview, Rose asks, &#8220;What is it about mountain climbing that captures our imagination?&#8221;</p>

<p>Viesturs’ response:</p>

<blockquote><p>It’s about plugging away at something that looks almost impossible. It’s about looking at something from the beginning to an end that seems almost unachievable. And then achieving that end.<br/></p>

<p>When I speak to corporate groups [about achieving a goal], my message is that if you’re passionate about it,<br/>
if you have a good team,<br/>
if you enjoy the process,<br/>
if you break it into steps,<br/>
you can achieve amazing things if you have the patience to do so.<br/></p></blockquote>

<p>Amazing things indeed.</p>

<p><em>Note: A version of this post originally appeared on the <a href="http://wisdomgroup.com">WisdomGroup Blog</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
