<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ruby | RayHightower.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/categories/ruby/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-12T23:13:33-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://RayHightower.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Raymond T. Hightower - Chicago Ruby on Rails & iOS Developer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Automatic ctags with RubyMotion and Vim]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/02/12/automatic-ctags-with-rubymotion-and-vim/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-12T19:35:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/02/12/automatic-ctags-with-rubymotion-and-vim</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2012/10/29/building-ios-apps-with-ruby-motion/">RubyMotion</a> includes a <code>rake</code> task that generates <a href="http://ctags.sourceforge.net/whatis.html">Exuberant Ctags</a>. To generate tags, run the following in the root directory of a RubyMotion project.</p>

<p><code>bash
$ rake ctags
</code></p>

<h4>Make Ctags Better With Automation</h4>

<p>Ctags make writing code more efficient. But we shouldn't have to type <code>$ rake ctags</code> every time we create a new RubyMotion project. This article shows how to use a shell script to generate ctags automatically every time you create a new RubyMotion app.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h4>How Ctags Save Time</h4>

<p>Ctags can save you time. For example, when creating a new class called <code>HomeViewController</code> that inherits from <code>UIViewController</code>, typing the first view characters of the superclass will produce the drop-down shown below.
<img src="http://RayHightower.com/images/uiviewcontroller.png" align="center" width="800" height="433" title="ctags RubyMotion Vim" alt="ctags RubyMotion Vim"></p>

<p>RubyMotion's implementation of ctags includes support for built-in iOS classes like UIViewController. The code completion and drop-downs offered by ctags will reduce keystrokes and errors, freeing the developer to focus on solving harder problems.</p>

<h4>Creating the</h4>

<p>Here's the . You can use any name that suits you. My script is called <code>mmotion.command</code> (with two m's at the beginning) and it's in <code>~/bin/</code>.</p>

<p>``` bash</p>

<h1>!/bin/bash</h1>

<h1>Create a RubyMotion app, change into the app's directory, and run ctags.</h1>

<h1>Written by Raymond T. Hightower on February 12, 2013</h1>

<p>echo "Creating a new RubyMotion app called:" $1
motion create $1
cd $1
echo "Creating ctags for the new RubyMotion app..."
rake ctags
echo "Opening the new app in Vim..."
mvim .
echo "To use the RubyMotion console, cd into the new directory:" $1
```
All of the work is done by by four lines. The remaining lines are comments or 'echos' that tell the user what's happening while the  is running.</p>

<h4>Running the</h4>

<p>If <code>~/bin/</code> is in the <code>$PATH</code>, you can run the  with the following line command:
<code>bash
$ mmotion.command [app name]
</code></p>

<p>Of course, we can still do better by leveraging the power of aliases in <code>~/.bash_profile</code>.</p>

<h4>Adding an Alias to ~/.bash_profile</h4>

<p>Dropping an alias into <code>~/.bash_profile</code> streamlines the process even more. You can use any alias you want as long as it doesn't confilct with another command. Here's what my alias looks like:</p>

<p><code>bash
alias mmotion="mmotion.command"
</code></p>

<h4>Taking the  for a Spin</h4>

<p>Now we can build a new RubyMotion app called <code>NewApp</code> with these
results:</p>

<p>``` bash
~/Code/Ruby/RubyMotion$ mmotion NewApp
Creating a new RubyMotion app called: NewApp</p>

<pre><code>Create NewApp
Create NewApp/.gitignore
Create NewApp/Rakefile
Create NewApp/app
Create NewApp/app/app_delegate.rb
Create NewApp/resources
Create NewApp/spec
Create NewApp/spec/main_spec.rb
</code></pre>

<p>Creating ctags for the new RubyMotion app...
Opening the new app in Vim...
To use the RubyMotion console, cd into the new directory: NewApp</p>

<p>~/Code/Ruby/RubyMotion$
```</p>

<p>After the bash  ends, it lands in the directory from which it was originally run, no matter what directories it changed to during execution. This script will open the new app in Vim when it's done.</p>

<p>From here, you can <code>$ cd NewApp</code> and type <code>rake</code> to run the app in the iOS simulator.</p>

<h4>Feedback Welcome</h4>

<p>If you notice any glitches with this approach, feel free to send me a "heads up" via the <a href="/contact/">contact</a> form on this site or in the blog comments below.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unix for Ruby Developers]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2012/12/24/unix-for-ruby-developers/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-24T16:50:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2012/12/24/unix-for-ruby-developers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://workingwithunixprocesses.com/"><img src="http://RayHightower.com/images/working-w-unix-processes.jpg" align="right" width="350" height="266"></a>
It is gratifying to know that learning something tangentially related to Ruby will, in fact, teach me more about Ruby.</p>

<p><a href="http://workingwithunixprocesses.com/"><em>Working With Unix Processes</em></a>, by Jesse Storimer, is ostensibly about Unix internals. However, in reading this book, I have become more aware of how executables run on my favorite family of operating systems, which in turn gives me more insight into Ruby.</p>

<h3>Passing Arguments</h3>

<p>For example, what happens when we pass arguments to a process, Ruby or otherwise? How do the arguments get there? Storimer offers a 1-line Ruby program called <code>argv.rb</code> that we can use to play with the ARGV array:</p>

<p>``` bash
~/Code/Ruby/apps/sandbox$ echo 'p ARGV' > argv.rb</p>

<p>~/Code/Ruby/apps/sandbox$ ruby argv.rb what results can we expect here
["what", "results", "can", "we", "expect", "here"]</p>

<p>~/Code/Ruby/apps/sandbox$</p>

<p>```</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Once we have our hands on the ARGV array, we can parse it and manipulate it at will.</p>

<h3>Grokking Forks</h3>

<p>The section on forks contains a lot of mind-bending fun. The author offers some code to explain how forks work, but some concepts are only understandable when we write our own code. I had to write my own in order to raise my comfort level with forks.</p>

<p>Here's what the code does:</p>

<ul>
<li>In the parent process, <code>fork</code> returns the <code>pid</code> of the child process.</li>
<li>In the child process, <code>fork</code> returns <code>nil</code>.</li>
<li>Therefore, the <code>if</code> block should be executed by the parent process...</li>
<li>...and the <code>else</code> block should be executed by the child process.</li>
</ul>


<p>``` ruby
puts "Parent process pid (before fork) is #{Process.pid}.\n"</p>

<p>if fork
  current_process = Process.pid
  parent_process = Process.ppid
  printf "Entered the <em>if</em> block during Process #{current_process}."
  printf "\nThe parent of this process is #{Process.ppid}, which should be bash.\n\n"
else
  current_process = Process.pid
  parent_process = Process.ppid
  printf "Entered the <em>else</em> block during Process #{current_process}."
  printf "\nThe parent of this process is #{parent_process}, which should be the original of this process.\n\n"
end</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>Running the above Ruby code produces the following results:</p>

<p>``` bash
~/Code/Ruby/apps/sandbox$ ruby forking_around.rb
Parent process pid (before fork) is 79703.
Entered the <em>if</em> block during Process 79703.
The parent of this process is 76751, which should be bash.</p>

<p>Entered the <em>else</em> block during Process 79704.
The parent of this process is 79703, which should be the original of this process.</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>Digging further: Let's look at the names that correspond to our
<code>pids</code>.</p>

<p>``` bash
~/Code/Ruby/apps/sandbox$ ps -p 79703
  PID TTY           TIME CMD</p>

<p>~/Code/Ruby/apps/sandbox$ ps -p 79704
  PID TTY           TIME CMD</p>

<p>~/Code/Ruby/apps/sandbox$ ps -p 76751
  PID TTY           TIME CMD
76751 ttys003    0:00.40 -bash</p>

<p>~/Code/Ruby/apps/sandbox$
```</p>

<p>We get zero data for the <code>pids</code> 79703 and 79704 because those processes terminated with the program <code>forking_around.rb</code>. However, 76751 shows <code>bash</code> because bash is still running.</p>

<p>The book is full of rich playground examples that go much deeper than this. Time slips away when I get rolling with this stuff!</p>

<h3>Errata Handling</h3>

<p>The book is new so you can expect a few typos. If you run into problems with sample code, a quick Google search will lead you to the corrected text. For example, early in the book I had problems with a command that returns the maximum number of processes allowed on a system. Turns out there was a typo, and <a href="http://forums.pragprog.com/forums/261/topics/11191">the correction</a> was posted by the author himself on the publisher's errata page.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>I enjoyed reading <em>Working With Unix Processes</em> because it replaces a belief in "the magic of Unix" with a sound understanding of Unix fundamentals. The book is clear and brief with plenty of examples. The author assumes that readers have at least a basic understanding of Ruby. After that, you only need a command line, IRB, and the willingness to explore.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ruby on Raspberry Pi]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2012/12/03/ruby-on-raspberry-pi/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-03T06:38:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2012/12/03/ruby-on-raspberry-pi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://RayHightower.com/assets/raspberry_pi_iphone.jpg" width="400" align="right" title="Raspberry Pi Circuit Board" alt="Raspberry Pi Circuit Board">
Raspberry Pi is a single-board computer roughly the size of a deck of cards. It's equipped with an ARM processor that runs Linux. USB ports let you attach a keyboard and mouse. Video is supported via HDMI and RCA. Storage is handled by SD cards. There's an Ethernet port.</p>

<p>You can buy a Raspberry Pi for $35.00.</p>

<h4>Will it Run Ruby?</h4>

<p>When my Raspberry Pi arrived, I was curious: Will it run Ruby? How about Rails?  This article describes my experience with RVM, Ruby, and Rails on a Raspberry Pi, along with the "gotchas" I encountered along the way.</p>

<!--more-->


<h4>Why Raspberry Pi?</h4>

<p>Raspberry Pi was created by a group of UK educators and engineers with a concern: Inexpensive hobbyist computers like the old Commodore 64 no longer exist. Game consoles continue to get better, but there is no replacement for the Commodore. As a result, young people who <em>might</em> become developers get introduced to the profession as gamers or users of Word or Excel. They begin as consumers, not creators. Sad news, because creators shape the world we all enjoy.</p>

<p>Creators get stronger when they have tools for learning, play, and <a href="/blog/2012/09/03/10000-hours-of-practice/">10,000 hours of practice</a>. Enter Raspberry Pi. It's a tiny, inexpensive computer. It runs open source software so it is highly accessible to curious minds that are eager to learn, practice, and play.</p>

<h4>Yes, It Will Run Ruby</h4>

<p>Here's a screenshot from my Raspberry Pi with the Midori web browser, RVM, Ruby 1.9.3-p327, Rails 3.2.9, Vim 7.3, and other tools. In this shot, I'm using the Pi's HDMI output to drive a 1080p monitor.</p>

<p><img src="http://RayHightower.com/assets/RaspberryPi-Desktop.png" width="800" align="middle" title="Raspberry Pi 1080p HDMI Monitor" alt="Raspberry Pi 1080p HDMI Monitor" ></p>

<p>Yes, this tiny, $35 device will drive a monitor at full 1080p HD.</p>

<h4>Getting Started</h4>

<p>Here's what you need to get Ruby running on your Raspberry Pi.</p>

<ul>
<li>1 Raspberry Pi with 512MB RAM or more. I bought mine from <a href="http://newark.com">Newark/element14</a>.</li>
<li>1 Monitor that accepts HDMI or RCA video input.</li>
<li>1 HDMI or RCA cable, depending on your monitor.</li>
<li>1 USB keyboard</li>
<li>1 USB mouse</li>
<li>1 8GB (or larger) SD card. The instructions recommend 4GB, but I suggest at least 8GB if you expect to run Rails. You'll need room for gems, git, etc.</li>
<li>1 Ethernet cable w/RJ-45 ends.</li>
<li>1 high-speed Internet connection.</li>
<li>A separate computer capable of writing an SD card image, or an SD card pre-configured for Raspberry Pi.</li>
</ul>


<p>The Pi makers have tested the device with SD cards as large as 32GB, even though 4GB is recommended. Personally, I prefer the larger cards because they allow more room for experiments.</p>

<h4>Prepping the SD Card</h4>

<p>The Pi's operating system boots from the SD card. There are several methods for prepping the SD card with the Raspberry Pi system. The easiest: Buy a Pi with a pre-configured SD card.</p>

<p>My Pi arrived before the pre-configured SD card. I'm a little bit impatient when it comes to new gadgets, so I decided to prep an old SD card of my own.</p>

<p><em>Note:</em> If you're reading this article, you already know the standard disclaimer about how technology changes rapidly therefore this procedure could be wrong by the time you read this. I've included links to references so you can check for updates on your own. You know the risks. Please backup everything that needs it.</p>

<p>References:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://elinux.org/RPi_Easy_SD_Card_Setup">eLinux SD Card Setup</a>. Methods for putting your preferred image on the SD card. I chose the "Copying an image to the SD card in Mac OS X (mostly graphical interface)" method.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.raspberrypi.org/downloads">Raspberry Pi Official Downloads</a>. Several SD card images, and a beginners wiki.</li>
</ul>


<p>Prepping an SD card takes a <em>long</em> time. In my case, it took 23 minutes from the time I executed the SD write command (<code>$ sudo dd...</code>) to the completion of the process. It was a little disconcerting because the system didn't do anything during that time. No feedback whatsoever. Sounds like an opportunity for a pull request!</p>

<h4>Starting the System</h4>

<p>To start your Raspberry Pi system:</p>

<ul>
<li>Plug the SD card, USB keyboard &amp; mouse, Ethernet cable, and video cable (HDMI or RCA) into their corresponding sockets.</li>
<li>Plug in the USB power adapter.</li>
</ul>


<p>There is no power switch. The device is turned on/off by adding or removing the power cable.</p>

<p>Linux will boot in text mode. When the system is done booting, you will be prompted for a username and password. Here are the default credentials:</p>

<pre><code>
raspberrypi login: pi
Password: raspberry
</code></pre>


<p>Several seconds later, you will be greeted with the $ prompt. You can continue to use the Pi in text mode, or you can start the X Window GUI with:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ startx
</code></p>

<h4>Ruby with RVM</h4>

<p>I am a big fan of <a href="http://rvm.io">Ruby Version Manager (RVM)</a>. I learn best when I break things. RVM's handling of Ruby versions and gemsets enables me to recover rapidly and well.</p>

<p>This command will install the latest stable versions of RVM and Ruby:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ curl -L https://get.rvm.io | bash -s stable --ruby
</code></p>

<p>It took over an hour for Ruby to compile on my Pi. The read/write speed of my SD card (Class 4) could have been a factor. I have a faster (Class 10) SD card on order.</p>

<h3>Installing Rails</h3>

<p>First, make sure you're using the version of Ruby you want to use.</p>

<p><code>bash
$ rvm current
</code></p>

<p>Next, create a gemset and tell RVM that you want to use it.</p>

<p><code>bash
$ rvm use [version of Ruby you want to use]
$ rvm gemset create firstgemset
$ rvm gemset use firstgemset
</code></p>

<p>And then install Rails as you would on any other 'nix-based machine.</p>

<p><code>
$ gem install rails
</code></p>

<h4>Gotchas</h4>

<p>The installation process was relatively smooth. Still, here are a few gotchas I encountered with the Pi:</p>

<ul>
<li>I already mentioned this, but it's worth repeating: It took 23 minutes to write the SD card, and there was no feedback along the way. This wasn't a big deal since I had been pre-warned by one of the wikis.</li>
<li>apt-get needed an update before I could install git. <code>$ sudo apt-get update</code> did the trick.</li>
<li>The Pi will do absolutely nothing without a properly configured SD card. You know how a PC will partially boot (to CMOS) even without a hard drive? Not so with the Pi.</li>
<li>The micro-USB power port requires 700mA or more of current. Most micro-USB power adapters deliver 500mA or less. Raspberry Pi will only boot if the micro-USB provides sufficient amperage. Only one of my several micro-USB adapters met this requirement.</li>
<li>A 4GB SD card is far too small if you want to do something useful with the Pi. My first Rails installation failed due to size limitations because I was using a 4GB card. Go with 8GB or larger.</li>
<li>I'm not 100% sure, but I think that a faster SD card will make a difference especially during the compilation of the Ruby interpreter. This is only a guess at this point. I don't yet know where the bottlenecks are.</li>
</ul>


<p>Overall, the gotchas were minor.</p>

<h4>For Screenshots, Try Scrot</h4>

<p>To take screenshots of the Raspberry Pi desktop, I used Scrot (SCReenshOT). Here's how to install Scrot:</p>

<p><code>
$ sudo apt-get install scrot
</code></p>

<p>After you install Scrot, this command will take a shot of the entire desktop and drop it into a file called <code>desktop.png</code> in your home directory.</p>

<p><code>
$ scrot ~/desktop.png
</code></p>

<p>To pause five seconds before taking the screenshot:</p>

<p><code>
$ sleep 5; scrot ~/desktop.png
</code></p>

<p><img src="http://RayHightower.com/assets/raspberry-pi-analog-TV.jpg" width="400" align="right" title="Raspberry Pi Analog TV Monitor" alt="Raspberry Pi Analog TV Monitor" ></p>

<h4>Analog TV</h4>

<p>Don't laugh: I still have an old analog TV in my living room. It's twelve years old and it still works. Since Raspberry Pi comes with multiple video outupts, analog TVs are useful again.</p>

<p>Here's Raspberry Pi running with my old analog TV as a monitor. Reminds me of the Commodore 64 days!</p>

<p>Raspberry Pi will work with a wide range of monitors, from HDMI to ancient analog. That makes the Pi accessible to a large audience of hobbyists and developers.</p>

<h4>Conclusion</h4>

<p>Raspberry Pi will never replace my primary machine because it's too slow. But it is certainly fast enough for learning. It meets the goals set forth by the engineering team.</p>

<p>I am excited by the learning opportunities offered by Raspberry Pi. To the Raspberry Pi Foundation: Thank you for an impressive device. I wish you much success.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building iOS Apps With RubyMotion]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2012/10/29/building-ios-apps-with-ruby-motion/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-29T18:49:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2012/10/29/building-ios-apps-with-ruby-motion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Special thanks to the organizers of <a href="http://magic-ruby.com/">MagicRuby</a> and <a href="http://aloharubyconf.com/">Aloha Ruby</a> for inviting me to present RubyMotion at their respective conferences. <a href="http://confreaks.com/videos/1245-aloharuby2012-building-ios-apps-with-rubymotion">Confreaks</a> recorded video at the Aloha Ruby event.</p>

<center>
<iframe name="rubymotionaloha" width="560" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/3gCsen5Zs4s" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</center>


<p>The fizzbuzz sample code can be found on <a href="https://github.com/RayHightower/fizzbuzzrm">GitHub</a>. Slides are on <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/rayhightower/building-ios-apps-with-rubymotion">SpeakerDeck</a>.</p>

<p>Should you use RubyMotion or Objective-C for iOS development? That depends...</p>

<!--more-->


<p>If your team is currently building web apps, and they happen to be Ruby-focused, then RubyMotion will enable you to create a <a href="http://rayhightower.com/blog/2012/08/31/four-steps-five-minutes/">minimum viable product (MVP)</a> using skills that you already have in-house. However, if your team is currently Objective-C focused, it may be easier for you to build your MVP in Objective-C.</p>

<p>Keep in mind that I am Ruby-biased, so I see advantages on the RubyMotion side of the question. Building the web <em>and</em> mobile pieces of an app in the same language means that expertise can be readily shared throughout the team. Shared expertise makes the team stronger.</p>

<p>Thanks again to MagicRuby and Aloha Ruby for asking me to speak, and to Confreaks for recording the talk.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
