<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Linux-Unix-OSX | RayHightower.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/categories/linux-unix-osx/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-09T19:39:22-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://RayHightower.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Raymond T. Hightower - Chicago Ruby on Rails & iOS Developer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unix for Ruby Developers]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2012/12/24/unix-for-ruby-developers/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-24T16:50:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2012/12/24/unix-for-ruby-developers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://workingwithunixprocesses.com/"><img src="http://RayHightower.com/images/working-w-unix-processes.jpg" align="right" width="350" height="266"></a>
It is gratifying to know that learning something tangentially related to Ruby will, in fact, teach me more about Ruby.</p>

<p><a href="http://workingwithunixprocesses.com/"><em>Working With Unix Processes</em></a>, by Jesse Storimer, is ostensibly about Unix internals. However, in reading this book, I have become more aware of how executables run on my favorite family of operating systems, which in turn gives me more insight into Ruby.</p>

<h3>Passing Arguments</h3>

<p>For example, what happens when we pass arguments to a process, Ruby or otherwise? How do the arguments get there? Storimer offers a 1-line Ruby program called <code>argv.rb</code> that we can use to play with the ARGV array:</p>

<p>``` bash
~/Code/Ruby/apps/sandbox$ echo 'p ARGV' > argv.rb</p>

<p>~/Code/Ruby/apps/sandbox$ ruby argv.rb what results can we expect here
["what", "results", "can", "we", "expect", "here"]</p>

<p>~/Code/Ruby/apps/sandbox$</p>

<p>```</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Once we have our hands on the ARGV array, we can parse it and manipulate it at will.</p>

<h3>Grokking Forks</h3>

<p>The section on forks contains a lot of mind-bending fun. The author offers some code to explain how forks work, but some concepts are only understandable when we write our own code. I had to write my own in order to raise my comfort level with forks.</p>

<p>Here's what the code does:</p>

<ul>
<li>In the parent process, <code>fork</code> returns the <code>pid</code> of the child process.</li>
<li>In the child process, <code>fork</code> returns <code>nil</code>.</li>
<li>Therefore, the <code>if</code> block should be executed by the parent process...</li>
<li>...and the <code>else</code> block should be executed by the child process.</li>
</ul>


<p>``` ruby
puts "Parent process pid (before fork) is #{Process.pid}.\n"</p>

<p>if fork
  current_process = Process.pid
  parent_process = Process.ppid
  printf "Entered the <em>if</em> block during Process #{current_process}."
  printf "\nThe parent of this process is #{Process.ppid}, which should be bash.\n\n"
else
  current_process = Process.pid
  parent_process = Process.ppid
  printf "Entered the <em>else</em> block during Process #{current_process}."
  printf "\nThe parent of this process is #{parent_process}, which should be the original of this process.\n\n"
end</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>Running the above Ruby code produces the following results:</p>

<p>``` bash
~/Code/Ruby/apps/sandbox$ ruby forking_around.rb
Parent process pid (before fork) is 79703.
Entered the <em>if</em> block during Process 79703.
The parent of this process is 76751, which should be bash.</p>

<p>Entered the <em>else</em> block during Process 79704.
The parent of this process is 79703, which should be the original of this process.</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>Digging further: Let's look at the names that correspond to our
<code>pids</code>.</p>

<p>``` bash
~/Code/Ruby/apps/sandbox$ ps -p 79703
  PID TTY           TIME CMD</p>

<p>~/Code/Ruby/apps/sandbox$ ps -p 79704
  PID TTY           TIME CMD</p>

<p>~/Code/Ruby/apps/sandbox$ ps -p 76751
  PID TTY           TIME CMD
76751 ttys003    0:00.40 -bash</p>

<p>~/Code/Ruby/apps/sandbox$
```</p>

<p>We get zero data for the <code>pids</code> 79703 and 79704 because those processes terminated with the program <code>forking_around.rb</code>. However, 76751 shows <code>bash</code> because bash is still running.</p>

<p>The book is full of rich playground examples that go much deeper than this. Time slips away when I get rolling with this stuff!</p>

<h3>Errata Handling</h3>

<p>The book is new so you can expect a few typos. If you run into problems with sample code, a quick Google search will lead you to the corrected text. For example, early in the book I had problems with a command that returns the maximum number of processes allowed on a system. Turns out there was a typo, and <a href="http://forums.pragprog.com/forums/261/topics/11191">the correction</a> was posted by the author himself on the publisher's errata page.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>I enjoyed reading <em>Working With Unix Processes</em> because it replaces a belief in "the magic of Unix" with a sound understanding of Unix fundamentals. The book is clear and brief with plenty of examples. The author assumes that readers have at least a basic understanding of Ruby. After that, you only need a command line, IRB, and the willingness to explore.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
